Welcome back in this lecture we're going to talk about Project environments a project environment describes
where the project works takes place.
So Project environments the physical location of where you're doing the project work but also the different
factors that influence the project.
So we need to understand the project environment first off the physical location.
We're doing construction.
Obviously there's a physical location we could be building way out in the middle of North Dakota.
There's not a lot of towns around there that a lot of resources around there.
So we have to plan much more precisely for the construction project in that remote location versus a
construction project in or near a city where if we need more equipment or we need a word or we need
some more bolts.
It's just a quick trip to the hardware store.
So the physical location affects the project planning and how we do the work.
It also can influence the project as far as return on investment in business value.
And if we choose to do the project.
So we need to understand the environment where the project will take place.
So things like the location of the project work.
These are physical environmental elements the working conditions so way out in Dakota there are parts
that are amazingly windy or snowy at different times versus in the south where it's it's hot and humid
or there's wildfires that are happening or you think about the physical environment if I'm in a secure
facility and you can't bring in your phone you know you can't take anything out with you.
Nothing in your pockets.
Maybe you're in a really secure facility or you're dealing with some sensitive data or you in a hospital
and they're hiper concerns and regulations you have to follow.
So the working conditions in the physical environment elements go together and that affects how you
manage how you plan it could slow down the effectiveness or efficiency because you have to accommodate
for those environmental elements.
Weather obviously is an environmental element but body wants to work in the rain or lightning storm
but constraints constraints or anything that limits your options.
So you're only allowed to be on the job site between 8:00 in the morning and six o'clock at night and
there's no construction on weekends.
You're not allowed to do any of the network updates during the daytime.
It has to be between 6:00 at night and 5:00 in the morning.
Whatever the case may be those are all constraints they limit your options in regard to having access
or the environmental elements constraints can also be just have to deal with it.
If you're out in North Dakota as I mentioned and there's snow there's rain there's wind.
There are not a lot of stores nearby to go get what she needs.
You have to come up with solutions so the constraints are anything that limits your options in regard
to environmental elements external enterprise environmental factors are the physical environmental elements
so member in E.F are things that are outside of the project off the outside of the organization external
environmental factors are things that restrict what you're allowed to do.
So some physical environmental elements could be you have to wear safety equipment and that is a factor
that's a law or an ocean regulation that you have to be secured and have safety harnesses on.
We're above so many feet or doing a particular type of work.
So any types of laws or regulations that affect your application area in a physical environmental element
are things that you have to consider.
Let's take a look at some social and cultural influences.
So the political climate of where your project takes place so talking about politics not only politics
and the government but how politics in your organization.
So you might have some fractions in your organization or you have departments that are being merged
together or absorbed and that can create a hostile environment for your project.
There are codes of conduct Yes.
We have a p.m.-I code of conduct but there might also be a code of conduct in your discipline in your
organization.
There are definitely ethics.
So you have to behave ethically and treat people kindly and with respect.
Perceptions perception is truth to the individual that is making that perception.
Like I'm making a perception that there's a real mystery around people that do software development
that I don't understand it.
So they must be really smart and really amazing people to work with and I respect whatever they say
because they say they're a software developer.
Now for a lot of software developers that's true.
But I think we all know there's this sliver of people that say they're software developers and they're
just really good at copy and paste.
It's the same it's you see it's everyone.
But that perception that people have about a role without a responsibility sometimes is not a true perception
and that can work the other way as well.
And I have a perception of oh I've worked with you know I've worked with technical writers before I've
worked with electricians for that company before.
They're no good because they have a perception of that type of work or that industry or that company
and it's not always a true perception.
So that can affect your project the values.
Yes business now you but also what's important to the stakeholders.
What's important to the project team members what's important to the project manager.
So think about the values in particular in this context that we're talking about the values of the customers
in the business and who's going to receive what we create for them.
And again external enterprise environmental factors anything that's outside of the organization.
So you think about the culture of the country where the work is taking place with the social aspects
of the project might have in your community that's an external enterprise environmental factor that
can affect your project.
Another thing to consider is the organizational culture and structure and I hinted at this a little
bit earlier when we talked about a big bank versus a small startup and how there may be a different
culture there because of the structure and the history and the maturity of those two different organizations.
So some things that influence the culture and the structure is a clear vision statement or a mission
statement for the organization.
What are the stated values and beliefs and then what's the values and beliefs of the people that work
in that organization.
What are the cultural norms.
Is it just excepted to write down a change request and send an email or put her on a Post-it note.
Is that how you get things done.
Is that a cultural norm or is it a cultural norm that everybody kind of kicks off Friday after lunch.
Like you know is always fun to do.
Or is it a cultural norm that you just don't schedule meetings on Friday after 10:00 a.m. you know like
get get that stuff done at the top of the week.
So what's the cultural norm where you work.
What's the hierarchy in the authority who reports to whom and is that clear among your project team.
What about the organizational in management style.
So how do people manage other people.
Is there respect there's more loose as a kind of a de facto management or is that a very clear distinction
of who's a manager and what are the different roles and what are their responsibilities.
And then we have internal enterprise environmental factors we've talked about external things outside
of the organization.
So internal or things that are created within the organization that affect your project.
So an example of an internal enterprise environmental factors are how you do procurement how you communicate
with the public how you discipline your project team members that's unique to your company and that
affects how you operate how you act as a project manager.
Another thing that we have to consider is the infrastructure this is an environmental factor the infrastructure
of where the work takes place.
So you think about the facilities.
Think about what equipment you can use is that really old equipment.
Is it brand new.
Is this a learning curve.
So what about the equipment What about communicating with one another.
So telecommunications channels are texting.
Is that allowed or are you able to send email send and receive via your phone.
What about out in the field or if you're in a secure environment.
And then I can't receive a text or a phone that don't have a signal or I'm not allowed to take my phone
into that job site with me.
So how will I communicate there.
What about sensitivity of that nature.
Ever since someone a text and you accidently sent it to the wrong person and then it blows up.
I've certainly done that.
I.T. hardware and usability.
So laptops you know workstations especially in an I.T. environment or you're using a very complex piece
of software you know a learning curve or can the hardware keep up with the demands of that software.
So what about I.T. hardware and usability.
And then again internal enterprise of our mental factors things that are created by your organization
that can affect your infrastructure they yet know you're not allowed to use texting you're not allowed
to use social media for work.
Everything has to go through a secure e-mail server you can't you know send it via Google you have to
use our e-mail server.
So those interim internal enterprise environmental factors were supposed to follow.
We have to follow as the project manager but we need to communicate that to our stakeholders into our
project team members what those are because that affects how we manage the project.
All right a lot of good information here in this lecture.
But keep moving forward you're doing great.
I'll see you in the next lecture.